Library Company of Philadelphia minute books LCP.Minutes
Library Company of Philadelphia
During the following year all the books were moved to the basement of the Ridgway Library under the supervision of Barney Chesnick. He had been hired to assist Samuel at Broad and Christian Streets and succeeded him in charge of the old collections then being used by a comparatively few discerning and imaginative scholars. The two-centuries-old Library Company was at the nadir of its fortunes. About this time, two studies looked at the Library Company's holdings and operations. They came to similar conclusions: that the circulation of modern books to members and subscribers was an obsolete service, and that the Library Company should become a research library, preferably in association with one of the city's other institutions. This required long-term planning. For the moment, the rent from the parking lot and income from endowment funds were not sufficient to pay for all the library's operating expenses. This situation, World War II, and Austin Gray's resignation as Librarian impelled the directors in 1943 to make arrangement with the Free Library of Philadelphia whereby that institution became the corporate librarian of the Library Company, responsible (for a fee) for the administration of the library. At about the same time, the Library Company's endowment funds were reorganized and brilliantly reinvested by Moncure Biddle, who in concert with the treasurer, W. Logan Fox, began to build a solid financial base for the institution.
The resurgent feeling that "something should be done" had been repressed during the 1930s and 1940s because the financial difficulties of the Library Company precluded any constructive change. Edwin Wolf 2nd was engaged to make a survey of the collections, to assess their scope, size, and importance, and to suggest means to improve their care and usefulness. Then, four eminent librarians - Lloyd A. Brown of the Peabody Institute, William A. Jackson of Harvard, Paul North Rice of the New York Public Library, and Clifford K. Shipton of the American Antiquarian Society - were invited to inspect the Library Company and consult with the directors about its future.
Unanimously, the experts agreed that the Library Company's greatest strength lay in its rare books and manuscripts, and that its greatest contribution to society would be as a scholarly research library with special emphasis on American history and culture. There was no doubt that the rare books and manuscripts were far more numerous and more valuable than had been generally believed. The first and immediate step the consultants urged was a program of rehabilitation. The most valuable books should be taken from the scattered locations, recatalogued, repaired, and temporarily reshelved in a room to be refitted and air-conditioned. Then the experts recommended that the Library Company reduce and refine its mass of late-nineteenth- and twentieth-century books, keeping only those which would supplement as reference works the basic historical collections.
These steps were, however, considered preliminary to a decision to move out of the Ridgway Library. That structure, once considered fireproof, was judged instead to be a fire-trap. Furthermore, the roof leaked, the basement was damp, and the building's location in the city was unfortunate. The consensus was that the Library Company should move to modern quarters in or adjacent to another compatible library as soon as possible.
By 1955, with income from the parking garage increasing, the Library Company could stand on its own feet. In December of that year, the arrangement with the Free Library was amicably terminated. Wolf became Librarian. He shared the excitement of rediscovery and revitalization with an audience of bookmen - librarians, collectors, booksellers, and, of course, members of the Library Company - through his paradoxically light yet scholarly essays in the Annual Reports.
The experts' primary recommendation - to move from the totally inadequate and unsuitable Ridgway Library - had not been forgotten. A location next to the Historical Society was favored. The steps necessary to bring the plan to fruition were interlocking and complicated. Fortunately, at the critical time the City of Philadelphia made a satisfactory offer for the building and land. The Library Company was given permission to make the sale and also to use such other funds as were part of the Rush estate to build the new library. Three nineteenth-century brownstone houses, owned by and contiguous to the Historical Society, were purchased and torn down. Plans for a modern eight-story building were drawn by the architectural firm of Carroll, Grisdale, and Van Alen, and construction began in 1964. Meanwhile, in order to carry out another of the original recommendations concerning the future of the Library Company and to avoid moving unwanted books, a sweep of the shelves was undertaken. With formal authorization from the directors and the membership as a whole, Wolf culled and disposed of such works printed after 1880 as were deemed not germane to the Library Company's main collections.
With the Library Company's holdings down to an estimated 375,000 volumes, the Library Company was ready to return to the center of the city. The new building was completed by the end of 1965. The difficult transfer of the books nevertheless provided an opportunity to revamp the shelving arrangement and gather together subject classes which the space problems in the old building had fragmented. Because approximately two-thirds of the funds for the new library derived from the Rush estate, the building, like its predecessor, was named the Ridgway Library. The building was opened to the public in April 1966. A reciprocal arrangement was reached with the neighboring Historical Society whereby its rare books are shelved and used by readers in the Library Company, and the latter's manuscripts are shelved and used by readers in the Historical Society.
An interest in eighteenth-century intellectual history led Wolf in 1956 to begin the reconstruction of three colonial private libraries which had been partly or wholly incorporated into the Library Company - those of James Logan, Benjamin Franklin, and William Byrd of Westover, Virginia. He published a definitive catalogue of Logan's library in 1974. The other two libraries had been scattered by 1800, but he was able to locate substantial parts of them on the Library Company's shelves and in other collections across the country.
Comparing the Library Company's holdings with already-published subject bibliographies uncovered still more collections of surprising strength in areas such as technology, Judaica, household and cookery books, courtesy books, gift books, and architecture. In the process of strengthening and extending the Library Company's core collection, unnecessary or expensive duplication of the holdings of other local libraries was always avoided. This principle was applied not only to individual books but to whole areas of collecting. All acquisitions still build on the core collection acquired between 1731 and 1880. The collection is constantly growing, but its essential character has not changed.
The move to the new Ridgway Library proved fruitful for the print collection of the Library Company as well. With the appointment of Stefanie A. Munsing as curator of prints in 1971, the Print Department was born and quickly became a center of activity. A vast task faced the new curator of reorganizing and cataloguing the accumulation of Philadelphia views, portraits, American political cartoons, and early photographs. In 1975, Bernard Reilly moved from the Reading Room to the Print Department. It was during his tenure and due to his initiative that the Library Company's remarkable collection of nineteenth-century Philadelphia photographs began to be appreciated.
In 1977, Kenneth Finkel took over the Print Department. Under his aggressive and imaginative curatorship from 1977 to 1994, the collection increased at a phenomenal rate. With the exhibition and simultaneous publication in 1980 of Nineteenth-Century Photography in Philadelphia, the Print Department became the center for the study of early photography in Philadelphia.
Conservation of the ever-growing collections grew in importance over the years. A bindery was first set up at the Library Company in 1954 by the German master bookbinder Fritz Eberhardt to repair and rebind in chronological order the vast collection of pamphlet Americana. After Eberhardt left in 1957, Kaspar Reder was hired to continue the work. The care of the print collection was taken up in 1971 with the bindery staff working under the guidance of Curator of Prints Stefanie Munsing. Under Chief of Conservation Jennifer Woods Rosner, the staff began to move systematically through the entire rare book collection, and its range of treatments has widened to include making protective boxes, reattaching covers detached from leather bindings, repairing cloth bindings of the 19th century, and replacing old library bindings with new ones made of high-quality archival materials.
Under the direction of Librarian Wolf, the Library Company assumed a leading role in the cultural and intellectual community of Philadelphia and established a reputation of scholarly service both locally and internationally. Franklinian common sense, with a dash of thrift, was its guide, as befit a library struggling to be reborn. Wolf retired at the end of 1984 and was succeeded by John C. Van Horne, who came to the Library Company from the American Philosophical Society. Under Van Horne's guidance the Library Company struck out in several new directions. The Library Company began to attract more scholars to the collections by instituting an endowed research fellowship program in 1987 that provides modest stipends to enable graduate students and senior scholars to travel to Philadelphia to conduct research at the Library Company. The Library Company also created a revolving Publication Fund that supports the publication of a variety of works, usually carrying the joint imprint of the Library Company and a commercial or university press co-publisher. These books are generally based on the collections or relate to special projects or programs.
In the second half of the twentieth century, the Library Company has been utterly transformed from a dusty mausoleum filled with books that were deteriorating from heat, damp, and dust, to a busy and vital center for research and education of national importance. The Library Company remains open and free of charge to any serious scholar, but the collections are now housed in closed stacks, and no rare materials circulate except as loans for exhibition in other institutions. The collections are constantly and vigorously expanded and enriched, and they are fully accessible through card catalogues and other in-house finding aids.
All these changes have been made in order to carry out the Library Company's new mission as articulated in the 1950s: to collect, preserve, and make available books, graphics, and other primary source materials for the study of American history and culture up to the closing years of the 19th century. Much has changed and will change, but one thing remains constant: the collections are the focus of all the library's energies, and the reason for its existence.
Bibliography:
Quoted directly, in segments from: At the Instance of Benjamin Franklin: A Brief History of The Library Company of Philadelphia, 1995 [full document available at: http://librarycompany.org/about/Instance.pdf]
Related Archival Materials note
Library Company of Philadelphia: Library Company of Philadelphia Shareholders records, 1732-2000.
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists of minute books documenting the meetings of the Directors (both final minutes and rough minutes), 1731 to 2000; the Trustees of the Loganian Library, 1853 to 1876; and the Committee for Fixing the Value of Lost Books, 1785 to 1848. Included in these volumes are financial reports and supporting materials such as excerpts from annual reports, exhibition announcements, menus and correspondence.
The "Directors' Minutes" are housed in volumes 1 to 24. Entries generally include: policies, book lists, copies of letters sent to the Library Company of Philadelphia, current financial status, members present for meetings, and committees created and the members appointed to those committees. Minutes books from 1731 to approximately 1938 are hand written, thereafter, the minutes are typed. Original letters and the report of the president are frequently pasted into the typed minutes. The proceedings of the Annual Meeting held on May 6, 1929 was transcribed and is included in this series.
The "Rough Minutes of the Directors' Meetings" run from 1850 to 1932 and appear to be the notes taken during the actual meeting which were later transcribed into the official record housed in "Directors' Minutes." Therefore, the information contained within these volumes is duplicate to the material contained in the previous series, however; these volumes do not contain original auxiliary material.
The "Minutes of the Trustees of the Loganian Library," consist of two volumes of minutes from 1792 to 1935, and two folders of rough minutes from 1853 to 1876. Again, these rough minutes were probably notes taken during the meeting, which were copied into the final minute books. When the Loganian Library was added to the collections of the Library Company of Philadelphia, in addition to the directors of the Library Company serving as Trustees, the eldest male descendent of James Logan and two others appointed by him were also to serve as Trustees. These minutes document the transactions of the meetings addressing specific Loganian Library issues.
The "Minutes of the Committee for Fixing the Value of Lost Books" consists of one volume dating from 1785 to 1848.
These volumes effectively tell the history of the Library Company of Philadelphia and document the establishment of and challenges of a 200 year old institution's struggles to maintain its mission, resources, and quality through financial and societal changes. Researchers interested in the history of the Library Company of Philadelphia, Philadelphia history, or libraries will find this collection to be of great value.
Library Company of Philadelphia.; Loganian Library.; Libraries; Minutes; Philadelphia (Pa.); Research libraries; Subscription libraries
- Series I. Directors' Minutes
  - Volume 1, 1731-1742
  - Volume 1 (photostat copy), 1731-1742 (Volume 1a)
  - Volume 2, 1768-1785
  - Volume 3, 1785-1794
  - Volume 4, 1794-1816
  - Volume 5, 1816-1832
  - Volume 6, 1832-1850
  - Volume 7, 1850-1875
  - Volume 8, 1875-1885
  - Volume 9, 1885-1901
  - Volume 10, 1901-1912
  - Volume 11, 1912-1924
  - Volume 12, 1924-1932
  - Transcription of Annual Meeting, 1929 May 6 (Volume 13)
  - Volume 13, 1932-1938 (Volume 14)
  - Volume 14, 1938-1941 (Volume 15)
  - Volume 15, 1941-1848 (Volume 16)
  - Volume 16, 1948-1958 (Volume 17)
  - Volume 17, 1958-1964 (Volume 18)
  - Volume 18, 1964-1970 (Volume 19)
  - Volume 19, 1970-1979 (Volume 20)
  - Volume 20, 1979-1985 (Volume 21)
  - Volume 21, 1986-1989 (Volume 22)
  - Volume 22, 1994-1997 (Volume 23)
  - Volume 23, 1998-2000 (Volume 24)
  - Microfilm of Volumes 1-3 (Reel 1)
- Series II. Rough Minutes of Directors' Meetings
  - 1850 May 9-1856 May 1 (Volume 25)
  - 1859 March 3-1864 December 4 (Volume 26)
  - 1868 November 5-1870 May 5 (Volume 27)
  - 1870 April 7-1873 May 1 (Volume 28)
  - 1873 May 5-1876 April 27 (Volume 29)
  - 1877 May 3-1877 June 7 (Volume 30)
  - 1881 June 6-1891 January 2 (Volume 31)
  - 1891 April 3-1900 November 1 (Volume 32)
  - 1900 December 6-1903 April 30 (Volume 33)
  - 1903 May 7-1906 May 3 (Volume 34)
  - 1906 June 7-1907 April 7 (Volume 35)
  - 1910-1915 (Volume 36)
  - 1915 December 2-1922 April 6 (Volume 37)
  - 1922-1931 (Volume 38)
  - 1932 (Volume 39)
  - Directors and Loganian Trustees, 1924-1926 (Volume 40)
- Series III. Minutes of the Trustees of the Loganian Library
  - Volume 1, 1792-1870 (Volume 41)
  - Volume 2, 1870-1936 (Volume 42)
  - 1853-1861 (Volume 43)
  - 1861 October 3-1876 February 3 (Volume 44)
- Series IV. Minutes of the Committee for Fixing the Value of Lost Books
  - 1785-1848 (Volume 45)